Guide to the Angier Biddle Duke papers, 1915-1990s and undated, bulk 1950-1995 RL.00326
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Angier Biddle Duke papers
1915-1990s and undated, bulk 1950-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995
RL.00326
94 Linear Feet
Chief of Protocol and ambassador to Spain, Morocco, and Denmark under the Kennedy, Johnson, and Carter administrations; resident of New York, N.Y., Long Island, N.Y., and Washington, D.C. The collection chiefly consists of correspondence; scrapbooks and diaries; photographs; diplomatic papers; sound recordings and films; interviews, appointment books; clippings; printed material; and business papers, all documenting Angier Biddle Duke's life and career, especially his role in United States politics and diplomacy during the Kennedy and Johnson administrations, as well as his philanthropic activities and his leadership roles in non-profit institutions. The materials also document the social and political activities of members of the Duke, Drexel, and Biddle families, and their residences in New York City and Long Island. In addition, the papers contain information on economic and social conditions in post-war Europe during Duke's ambassadorship to Spain, and information on Pakistani refugees and other international crises. Other topics include civil rights and desegregation (especially in Washington, DC).
Approx. 46,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, but some use restrictions apply.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Some use copies are available; otherwise, access to materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Angier Biddle Duke papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1973 to 1995.
Biographical Note
1915 Born in New York City, Nov. 30, son of Angier Buchanan and Cordelia (Biddle) Duke
1934-1937 Attended Yale University
1937 Married first wife, Priscilla St. George. Had one son by her, Angier Pony St. George Duke (b. 1938)
1939 Divorced Priscilla St. George
1940 Married Margaret Screven White
1940-1945 Served in U.S. Army; promoted from Private to Major
1945 Officer in charge of Air Transport Command, Paris section
1945-1948 President, Duke International Corporation, NYC
1949 Appointed to U.S. Foreign Service
1949 Appointed to post in American Embassy, Buenos Aires, Argentina
1951 Special Assistant to Ambassador, American embassy, Madrid, Spain
1952 Divorced Margaret Screven White
1952 Married Maria-Luisa de Aranha, Dec. 11. Had two children by her: Maria Luisa (Marylou) Biddle Duke (b. 1954) and Dario Drexel Duke (b. 1957)
1952-1953 U.S. Ambassador to El Salvador (youngest ambassador in US at 36 years old)
1954-1960 President, International Rescue Commission
1955-1961 Commissioner, Long Island State Park
1957 Received LL. D., Iona College
1958-1960 V.P. of CARE
1961 Maria-Luisa killed in plane crash, Queens, NY
1961-1965 Chief of Protocol, U.S. Department of State, Kennedy and Johnson administrations
1962 Married Robin Chandler Lynn, May 12. Had one son by her, Angier Biddle Duke, Jr. (b. 1963)
1965-1968 Ambassador to Spain
1968 Chief of Protocol, U.S. Department of State
1968-1969 Ambassador to Denmark
1969 LL. D., Duke University
1973-1976 Commissioner of Civic Affairs and Public Events, NYC
1974-1995 Director, Appeal of Conscience Foundation
1976-1977 Chairman, NYC Democratic Committee
1977-1979 President, The Spanish Institute, NYC (chairman, 1983-1987)
1978-1979 President, National Committee on American Foreign Policy, Inc. Chairman, NY State Council on Ethnic Affairs
1979-1981 Ambassador to Morocco, Carter administration
1981-1990 Trustee, Long Island University
1981-1986 Chairman, U.S.-Japan Foundation, NYC
1981-1995 Chairman, World Affairs Council, Long Island
1986-1990 Chancellor, Long Island University, Southampton Campus
1988-1995 Chairman, Duke Family Association of NC
1992-1995 President, Council of American Ambassadors
1995 Died, Southampton, Long Island
Collection Overview
The collection chiefly consists of correspondence; scrapbooks and diaries; photographs; diplomatic papers; sound recordings and films; interviews, appointment books; clippings; printed material; and business papers, all documenting Angier Biddle Duke's life and career, especially his role in United States politics and diplomacy during the Kennedy and Johnson administrations, as well as his philanthropic activities and his leadership roles in non-profit institutions. The materials also document the social and political activities of members of the Duke, Drexel, and Biddle families, and their residences in New York City and Long Island. In addition, the papers contain information on economic and social conditions in post-war Europe during Duke's ambassadorship to Spain, and information on Pakistani refugees and other international crises. Other topics include civil rights and desegregation (especially in Washington, DC).
Details on Angier Biddle Duke's life as well as information on the Duke, Biddle, and Drexel families can be found in the Biographical Data Series. These materials include some of A.B. Duke's military records; articles on A.B. Duke; articles and biographical entries on A.B. Duke; "in memoriam" booklets from his first wife's funeral and the funeral of Angier Buchanan Duke, A.B. Duke's father; and genealogical materials on the families. Selected condolences out of the hundreds sent to Robin Chandler Duke after her husband's death in 1995 also reveal much about the personality and life of A.B. Duke. In addition, the narratives in the Diaries Series offer a great deal of material concerning the personalities of A.B. Duke and his family and acquaintances throughout his life.
The Correspondence Series also offers information on the Duke, Biddle, Semans, and Trent families, though correspondence between immediate family members makes up a small percentage of this large series. The correspondence files are most useful for the documentation they provide about A.B. Duke's career. Additional biographical data on A.B. Duke and family members, particularly useful for information on Robin Chandler Duke's social and political activities, can be found in the Clippings Series.
The Photograph Albums and Photographs Series contains hundreds of photographs of the Duke, Semans, and Biddle families. Some early photographs of Angier Biddle Duke were taken during his enlistment in the Army from 1940-1945. An album entitled "A celebration of the life of Benjamin Newton Duke, 1979" can be found in the Scrapbooks Series. Finally, as A.B. Duke served as president of the Duke Family Association of NC from 1988-1995, there are a number of items related to the meetings of this genealogical association found in the Correspondence Series.
Angier Biddle Duke was best known for his ambassadorial skills and his political acumen beginning with his appointment to the office of Ambassador to El Salvador in 1952 as the youngest ambassador ever appointed to a post. His subsequent career in diplomacy and politics, including his appointment as Chief of Protocol under Presidents Kennedy and Johnson, is well-documented throughout the majority of the series. A series of written and taped diaries entitled the "Ambassador's Diary" are especially interesting for A.B. Duke's candid reflections on his experiences.
The political and social events of the 1960s and 1970s are well-represented in the papers in the multimedia formats associated with the Audio, Film, and Videotape Series, containing numerous recordings of speeches, toasts, and visits of foreign dignitaries; the Scrapbooks and Photograph Albums and Photographs Series, which hold many candid and formal photographs of politicians, diplomats, celebrities, and artists; and the Clippings Series. One scrapbook covers President Kennedy's trip to Berlin, West Germany; another oversize scrapbook covers an international incident at Palomares, Spain (1966): while Duke was that country's ambassador, an undetonated U.S. nuclear bomb was lost off the coast of Spain, then recovered after an increased international outcry against nuclear weapons. Materials in the Protocol Papers Series also concern Kennedy's assassination and the transition to a Johnson White House during the period when A.B. Duke was Chief of Protocol. As Jacqueline Kennedy had already become a good friend of A.B. Duke's family, there are items in the Correspondence Series reflecting her close relationship with them in the difficult years after her husband's assassination.
The head of the State Department Office of Protocol serves as principal adviser to the President and Secretary of State on matters of diplomatic procedures governed by law or international customs and practice. Angier Biddle Duke's responsibilities as Chief of Protocol from 1961-1965 and 1968, including his role in the arrangements for the Kennedy funeral, are best represented by materials in the Protocol Papers Series, arranged alphabetically by country, and by many valuable letters and telegrams in the Correspondence Series, and in the Writings and Speeches Series. In addition, a great deal of relevant information, both contemporary and retrospective in nature, can be found in the Interviews Series. Several important volumes in the Scrapbooks and Diaries Series are also were created as records of his tenure as Chief of Protocol, and the Pictures Series contains many candid and formal photographs during this period. Finally, events relating to the Office of Protocol are found in audio or film format in the Audio, Film, and Video Series. Memorabilia from this period such as invitations, dinner menus, guest lists, and souvenir programs from inaugurations abroad can also be found in the Miscellaneous Series.
A.B. Duke's extensive organizational activities in later decades are documented in the Correspondence, Subject Files, Interviews, Printed Materials, and Writings and Speeches Series. A large number of materials reflect A.B. Duke's long involvement in the administration of Long Island University as well as in other institutions such as the International Rescue Commission, various Democratic committees, CARE, the NYC Dept. of Civic Affairs and Public Events, the Spanish Institute, the Appeal to Conscience Foundation, the Japan-American Institute, the World Affairs Council, and the American Council of Ambassadors, and many others. The Subject Files and other series also illustrate A.B. Duke's later involvement in organizations attempting to establish more democratic structures in countries such as El Salvador, Nicaragua, and Guyana.
Some materials also reflect Robin Chandler Duke's later involvement in politics, including her unsuccessful bid for the Democratic nomination to fill Koch's congressional seat in 1978, and her role as chairwoman of Population Action International.
Although they contain relatively few documents, the Legal and Financial Papers provide some information on A.B. Duke's income and financial activities, and on the Doris Duke Trust; also in the legal papers is a publisher's contract for the biography of Doris Duke and a copy of Angier Buchanan Duke's will. Other legal and financial matters related to the Duke and Biddle families, particularly the Doris Duke estate (1995) are referred to on a regular basis in the Correspondence Series. Very little is to be found in the collection on the administration, maintenance, or acquisition of Angier Biddle Duke's residences in Washington, NYC, or Long Island, though some illustrations of residences can be found in the Clippings and Pictures Series.
Collections in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library which contain information relevant to the Angier Biddle Duke Papers include the James Buchanan Duke Papers and especially the Semans Family Papers. The Duke University Living History Program collection, also in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, contains an interview with Angier Biddle Duke recorded in the 1970s.
Conditions Governing Access note
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Some use copies are available; otherwise, access to materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Diplomats -- Correspondence; Diplomacy -- 20th century; World politics -- 20th century; Philanthropists -- United States; Spain -- Foreign relations -- 1939-1975; Spain -- History -- 1939-1975; Civil rights movements -- United States; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History; Morocco -- History; Long Island (N.Y.); Denmark -- Foreign relations -- 1947-1972; World War, 1939-1945; Europe -- History -- 1945-; Denmark -- History -- 1900-; United States -- Foreign relations -- 20th century; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Videocassettes; Audiocassettes; Audiotapes; Photograph albums; Diaries; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Drexel family; Biddle family; Duke family; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963
- Biographical Data Series, 1923-1980s (bulk 1970s-1980s), 3 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  Primarily biographical sketches and articles on Angier Biddle Duke, a few military records, "in memoriam" booklets for his first wife, Maria-Luisa de Aranha Duke and Angier Buchanan Duke, his father (d. 1923), and genealogical material and other information on the Duke, Semans, Drexel, and Biddle families, including some photocopies of early Duke family photographs. Also contains a group photograph of Semans and Trent family members.
  - Biographical data (Box 1)
- Financial Papers Series, circa 1970s-1990s, 3 folders
  Personnel records, tax statements, receipts, itemized expenses, and schedules of campaign contributions by A.B. Duke.
  - Financial papers (Box 1)
- Legal Papers Series, circa 1970s-1980s, 3 folders
  Publisher's contract related to Doris Duke biography, document related to the Doris Duke Trust (1978), and documents from a 1978 lawsuit involving "Pony" Duke. Also includes a copy of Angier Buchanan Duke's will (1928).
  - Legal papers (Box 1)
- Interviews Series, circa 1960s-1980s, 8 folders
  Transcripts of interviews given by Angier Biddle Duke. There are also a few interviews given by Brzezinski and several ambassadors. Some of the tapes are in the Audio, Film, and Video Series. Interviews are in rough date order. One lengthy interview of A.B. Duke (only titled as "Interview 51," circa 1980,) is particularly rich in details on his personal and professional life.
  - Interviews (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1925-1995 (bulk 1960s-1995)
  Letters, photocopies and carbon copies of letters, telegrams, faxes, some invitations, and condolences. Correspondents include A.B. Duke, members of his immediate family, other relatives and friends, and well-known political figures and celebrities. Some of the correspondents include President Lyndon Johnson, Jacqueline Kennedy, Edward M. Kennedy, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., Cyrus Sulzberger, Adlai Stevenson, Coretta Scott King, Henry Ford II, Richard Nixon, Hubert Humphrey, Dean Rusk, Cyrus Vance, Prime Minister James Callahan, Albert Gore, Jimmy Carter, Jay Rutherfurd, Walter Annenberg, and many prominent ambassadors. Many are condolences on the sudden death of A.B. Duke's wife, Maria-Luisa de Aranha Duke in 1962, and many are congratulations offered upon his appointments to prominent positions. There are also many condolences sent to Robin Chandler Duke after A.B. Duke's death in 1995.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically, with some overlap of materials covering later decades.
  - 1925-1960; also has one folder of photocopies of letters relating to Duke's involvement with Kennedy family from 1961-1969. (Box 2)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 4)
  - 1966-1969 (Box 5)
  - 1970-1975 (Box 6)
  - 1975-1979 (Box 7)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 8)
  - 1980-1982 (Box 9)
  - 1981-1985 (Box 10)
  - 1976-1990 (bulk 1986-1990) (Box 11)
  - 1972-1994 (bulk 1990-1994) (Box 12)
  - 1980-1994 (bulk 1989-1994) (Box 13)
  - 1974-1995 (Box 14)
  - 1994-1995 (chiefly condolences to his wife on A.B. Duke's death) (Box 15)
  - 1995 (chiefly condolences) (Box 16)
  - 1963-1995 (bulk 1995; chiefly condolences) (Box 17)
- Diaries Series, 1938-1992, bulk 1961-1988)
  Diaries, memoirs, and journals belogning to A.B. Duke. Formats include handwritten volumes, handwritten sheets, typed drafts, transcripts of tapes, and audio cassettes. Some of the audio tapes are micro-cassettes; A.B. Duke's hand-held dictation recorder is located with the materials.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [Originals closed to use. Staff must arrange to have use copies made before materials can be accessed. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this collection.]
  - Chief of Protocol, 1961-1964 (Box 18)
  - U.S. Ambassador to Spain, 1966-1965 (2 vols.) (Box 18)
  - 1956, undated (2 vols.) (Box 18)
  - 1938-1940 (Box 18)
  - Transcripts
    - undated, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Mrs. Angier Biddle Duke: Notes from Brazil, Bolivia and Peru, 1976, Apr. (Box 18)
  - Tapes, undated (4 vols.) (Box 18)
  - Tapes, undated (6 vols.) (Box 19)
  - 1971-1982, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - 1941-1967 (12 folders, 1 vol.) (Box 20)
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Some use copies are available; otherwise, use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - 1941-1967 Audiocassettes (Master Tapes) (Box 20A)
  - 1941-1967 Audiocassettes (Use Tapes copy 1) (Box 20B)
  - 1941-1967 Audiocassettes (Use Tapes copy 2) (Box 20C)
  - Tapes, undated (2 boxes) (Box 21)
  - 1974, 1988, 1992, undated, 2 folders (Box 21)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1950s-1990s and undated
  Transcripts, drafts, and notes of toasts, speeches, remarks, testimony, and addresses given by A.B. Duke. Organizations sponsoring events include: the White House, the Spanish Institute, Overseas Press Club, National Press Club, and the Council of American Ambassadors. Events include White House Department of State functions, commencements, etc. Includes a speech given at Duke University Library in 1979, and remarks as chairman of the Duke Family Association of NC for the Sesquicentennial Founders' Day at Duke, 1988. Also includes testimony given by Duke for the House Foreign Affairs Committee and farewell speeches upon his leaving various ambassadorships. Other recordings of speeches and ceremonies can be found in the Audio, Film, and Video Series.
  - 1969-1968, undated, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - 1950s-1990s, 11 folders (Box 22)
  - 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - circa 1960s-1980s, undated, 11 folders (Box 23)
- Protocol Papers Series, 1961-1965, 1968
  Consists of correspondence and other documents such as event schedules, guest lists, and travel arrangements for various events, most of them centering on visiting foreign dignitaries. Several files relate to the funerals of John Kennedy, Martin Luther King, and Douglas McArthur.
  Arranged alphabetically by country and occasionally by event. Folders for the letter "F" were not present in the collection at the time of processing.
  - Afghanistan (Box 24)
  - Algeria (Box 24)
  - Arabian Peninsula (Box 24)
  - Argentina (Box 24)
  - Australia (Box 24)
  - Austria (Box 24)
  - Barbados (Box 24)
  - Bolivia (Box 24)
  - Brazil (Box 24)
  - Burma (Box 24)
  - Burundi (Box 24)
  - Cameroon (Box 24)
  - Canada (Box 24)
  - Chile (Box 24)
  - Costa Rica (Box 24)
  - Dane (Box 24)
  - Ethiopia, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Ecuador (Box 24)
  - Germany (Box 24)
  - Great Britain (Box 24)
  - Greece (Box 24)
  - Hawaii (Box 24)
  - Honduras (Box 24)
  - Iceland (Box 24)
  - India (Box 24)
  - Iran (Box 24)
  - Ireland, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Israel (Box 24)
  - Italy, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Japan (Box 24)
  - Johnson, Lyndon Baines: Visit to San Salvador, El Salvador (Box 25)
  - Jordan, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Kennedy, John Fitzgerald: Trips to Europe, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Kennedy, John Fitzgerald: Funeral, 1963 (Box 25)
  - Kennedy, Robert Francis: Funeral, 1968 (Box 25)
  - King, Martin Luther, funeral, 1968 (Box 25)
  - Laos (Box 25)
  - Libya (Box 25)
  - Luxembourg (Box 25)
  - MacArthur, Douglas, funeral (Box 25)
  - Malagasy Republic (Box 25)
  - Malaysia (Box 25)
  - Mauritania (Box 25)
  - Mauritius (Box 25)
  - Mexico (Box 25)
  - Morocco, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - New Zealand (Box 25)
  - Norway (Box 25)
  - "Operational Sail" (Box 25)
  - Pakistan (Box 25)
  - Philippines (Box 25)
  - Rwanda (Box 25)
  - Senegal (Box 25)
  - Somali Republic (Box 25)
  - Tanzania (Box 25)
  - Thailand (Box 26)
  - Trinidad (Box 26)
  - Tunisia, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Turkey (Box 26)
  - Uganda (Box 26)
  - Venezuela (Box 26)
  - Yugoslavia (Box 26)
  - Miscellany, 2 folders (Box 26)
- Scrapbooks Series, 1920s-1992
  Bound scrapbooks varying greatly in size, related to A.B. Duke's personal and professional activities. Contents include photographs, clippings, and other printed materials. Many are large-format, 16 x 20 inches and over. Series is unarranged.
  [As these albums are fragile, please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use these materials. May require conservation treatment before use.]
  - First Plattsburg Training Regiment, 1940 (Box 27)
  - The Dukes (Madrid - Washington), 1968 (Box 28)
  - A.B. Duke, 1956 (Box 29)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 30)
  - Argentina - Spain, 1951 (Box 31)
  - Poland, circa 1939-1955 (Box 31)
  - circa 1950-1951 (Box 32)
  - 1976 (Box 32)
  - circa 1954-1956 (Box 33)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 34)
  - The Statue of Liberty, Ellis Island, and Centennial Commission, 1992 (Box 35)
  - Wedding pictures, etc., circa 1950s (Box 36)
  - Africa, El Salvador, circa 1950s (Box 37)
  - 1958 (Box 38)
  - Palomares, Spain, 1966, Jan.17-Apr. 8 (Box 39)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 40)
  - History of the New York City Department of Civic Affairs and Public Events, 1974-1975 (Box 40)
  - 1965 (Box 41)
  - 1958 (Box 42)
  - San Salvador (Box 43)
  - A Celebration of the Life of Benjamin Newton Duke, 1979 (Box 43)
  - circa 1920s-1950s (Box 44)
  - Chief of Protocol, 1962 (Box 45)
  - Spain, 1966 (Box 46)
  - 1946-1956 (Box 47)
  - 1950s (Box 47)
  - Chief of Protocol, 1961 (Box 48)
- Photograph Albums and Photographs Series, circa 1930s-1990s and undated
  Chiefly photograph albums compiled by the Biddle family. There are also a few boxes of loose photographs. Includes formal photographs as well as many candid shots. Subjects include family, friends, and colleagues of Angier Biddle Duke, as well as many prominent politicians and dignitaries, and celebrities. There are many images of the Kennedy family. Subjects also include events such as the Zellerbach Commission's tour of post-war Europe, and often depict residences and estates.
  Series is arranged in original order as received.
  [Some albums are fragile and may require conservation treatment before use: please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use these materials.]
  - Album, circa 1950s (Box 49)
  - Album: The Zellerbach Commission: The Commission's Tour of Europe, 1957-Oct.15-Nov. 1 (Box 49)
  - Album: Barcelona, undated (Box 50)
  - Album: Visit to Headquarters, US Air Forces in Europe, Wiesbaden, Germany, 1967. (Box 50)